George Gamow and Barbara Gamow Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
George Gamow and Barbara Gamow Papers 1915-1975 (bulk 1950-1975)
MSS21899
Gamow, George, 1904-1968
Gamow, Barbara, 1905-1976
8,000 items
31 containers plus 1 oversize
13 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
George Gamow, physicist, astronomer, and author. Barbara Gamow, editor and translator. Correspondence, drafts of speeches, articles, and books, and other papers relating principally to George Gamow's career as an astronomer, physicist, and popularizer of science and to Barbara Gamow's personal and literary associations.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Alpher, Ralph, 1921-2007--Correspondence.; Bedford, Sybille, 1911-2006--Correspondence.; Brakhage, Stan--Correspondence.; Brosche, P. (Peter)--Correspondence.; Broughton, James, 1913-1999--Correspondence.; Cockcroft, John, Sir, 1897-1967--Correspondence.; Covici, Pascal, 1885-1964--Correspondence.; Critchfield, Charles Louis, 1910- --Correspondence.; Cummings, E. E. (Edward Estlin), 1894-1962--Correspondence.; Dirac, P. A. M. (Paul Adrien Maurice), 1902-1984--Correspondence.; Friedlander, Bernard Z.--Correspondence.; Friedman, Elizebeth, 1892-1980--Correspondence.; Friedman, William F. (William Frederick), 1891-1969--Correspondence.; Gamow, Barbara, 1905-1976. George Gamow and Barbara Gamow papers. 1915-1975.; Gamow, George, 1904-1968.; Guérard, Albert Léon, 1880-1959--Correspondence.; Herman, Robert, 1914- --Correspondence.; Holden, Raymond P. (Raymond Peckham), 1894-1972--Correspondence.; Hooker, Edward Niles--Correspondence.; Hooker, Evelyn Caldwell--Correspondence.; Hynek, J. Allen (Joseph Allen), 1910- --Correspondence.; James, Frances Theiss--Correspondence.; James, Garner--Correspondence.; Lord, Eda--Correspondence.; Mansbridge, Ronald--Correspondence.; Martin, John, 1865-1947--Correspondence.; Morehouse, Marion, 1906-1969--Correspondence.; Mott, N. F. (Nevill Francis), Sir, 1905- --Correspondence.; Norman, Charles, 1904- --Correspondence.; Searle, Ronald, 1920-2011--Correspondence.; Szent-Györgyi, Albert, 1893-1986--Correspondence.; Teller, Edward, 1908-2003--Correspondence.; Velikovsky, Immanuel, 1895-1979.; Yčas, Martynas, 1917- --Correspondence.
Subjects
Arithmetic.; Astronomy.; Astrophysics.; Big bang theory.; Cell nuclei.; Cosmology.; Genetics.; Literature.; Nuclear energy.; Number theory.; Physics.; Publishers and publishing.; Quasars.; RNA.; Science--History--20th century.
Titles
Barbara Gamow papers; George Gamow papers
Occupations
Astronomers.; Authors.; Editors.; Physicists.; Translators.
Provenance
The papers of George Gamow, physicist, astronomer, and author, and his wife, Barbara Gamow, editor and translator, were given to the Library of Congress by the Gamows and others, 1964-2009.
Transfers
Items have been transferred from the Manuscript Division to other custodial divisions of the Library. Photographs have been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division. Phonograph records and audiotapes have ben transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division. All transfers are identified in these divisions as part of the Gamow collection.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of George and Barbara Gamow are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
George Gamow
Date Event
1904, Mar. 4 Born Georgii Antonovic Gamov, Odessa, Russia
1928 Ph.D., physical science, University of Leningrad, Leningrad, USSR
1928 1929 Institute of Theoretical Physics, Copenhagen, Denmark
1929 1930 Rockefeller fellow, Cambridge University, Cambridge, England
1931 Married Lyubov Rho Vokhminzeva (divorced 1956) Published The Constitution of Atomic Nuclei and Radioactivity. Oxford: Clarendon Press
1931 1933 Professor, University of Leningrad, Leningrad, USSR
1933 1934 Lecturer, Paris, France, London, England, and University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, Mich.
1934 1956 Professor of physics, George Washington University, Washington, D.C.
1935 Collaborated with Edward Teller on the theory of beta-decay, and formulated the so-called "Gamow-Teller Selection Rule for Beta Emission"
1939 Proposed neutrino theory of supernovae Published Mr. Tompkins in Wonderland. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press
1940 Became naturalized American citizen Published The Birth and Death of the Sun. New York: Viking Press
1941 Published Biography of the Earth; Its Past, Present, and Future. New York: Viking Press
1942 Shell model of red giant stars
1947 Published One, Two, Three...Infinity. New York: Viking Press
1948 Theory of the origin of chemical elements
1952 Published The Creation of the Universe. New York: Viking Press
1956 Awarded Kalinga Prize by Unesco for popularization of science
1956 1968 Professor of physics, University of Colorado, Boulder, Colo.
1958 Published Matter, Earth, and Sky. Englewood Cliffs, N.J.: Prentice-Hall Married Barbara Merrihew Perkins
1961 Published Biography of Physics. New York: Harper
1968, Aug. 20 Died, Boulder, Colo.
1970 Posthumous publication My World Line. New York: Viking Press
Barbara Gamow
Date Event
1905, May 22 Born Barbara Merrihew Perkins, San Francisco, Calif.
1938 Married J. R. de la Torre Bueno (divorced circa 1943)
circa 1950 1958 Employed by Cambridge University Press
1958 Married George Gamow
1976 Died
Scope and Content Note
The papers of George Gamow (1904-1968) and Barbara Gamow (1905-1976) cover the period 1915 to 1975, but the bulk of the collection originates after 1950. George Gamow's papers, which constitute about two-thirds of the total, are concentrated in the years 1960-1968 and are chiefly scientific and professional. Barbara Gamow's papers consist primarily of personal and literary correspondence from 1928 to 1975. The collection is organized in Family Correspondence, General Correspondence, Personal Correspondence of Barbara Gamow, Speeches and Writings, Miscellany, Addition, and Oversize series.
Broad in scope, the papers provide source material for biographical studies and for the scientific and intellectual history of the period. Topics treated include theoretical physics, astrophysics, big bang theory, nuclear energy, nuclei, quasistellar objects, genetic coding, RNA coding, and number theory.
Well known in academic fields as a physicist and astronomer, George Gamow was perhaps more widely known to the world at large for his work as a popularizer of scientific literature. In the Speeches and Writings File are examples of both aspects of Gamow's work. There is various material about Mr. Tompkins, the fictitious bank clerk with a scientific curiosity whom Gamow used in his books for lay readers. There are also first drafts of several of his other books, numerous published and unpublished articles, and various original drawings and illustrations for texts. Other drawings for books and for Gamow's personal use are in the Miscellany series.
George Gamow's professional and scientific correspondence as well as the Gamows' social correspondence is in the General Correspondence series. Of especial interest for the scientist or scientific historian is Gamow's correspondence with Ralph Alpher and Robert Herman on the big bang theory, with Charles Critchfield on nuclear energy and nuclei, with Paul Dirac on gravity, with Martynas Yčas on the origination of the genetic code (with specific reference to RNA coding), and also posthumous letters to Gamow from all over the world. There is, however, virtually no correspondence prior to 1950; all discussion of scientific theory is related to developments after that date. This limitation in chronology, as reported by Barbara Gamow in 1964 correspondence with the Library of Congress, is due to George Gamow's tendency to destroy incoming letters once he had answered them and to keep no copies of outgoing correspondence. Many of George Gamow's original letters, as well as photocopies of originals, do exist in the collection, but not in great bulk. Among his significant correspondents are Sir John Cockcroft, Pascal Civici, Albert Einstein, William F. Friedeman and Elizabeth Friedman, J. Allen Hynek, Ronald Mansbridge, Sir Nevill Mott, Ronald Searle, Albert Szent-Györgyi, and Edward Teller.
The Personal Correspondence series consists of letters to and from Barbara Gamow. Married to J. R. de la Torre Bueno, a scholar and editor, from 1938 to 1943, and to George Gamow from 1958 until his death in 1968, she spent most of her career in the publishing business and was acquainted with writers, illustrators, editors, and others in the world of publishing. From 1958 to 1970, much of Barbara Gamow's time was spent editing and translating for her husband and carrying on some of his professional correspondence. Although she herself did not publish any books, she wrote verse for some of George Gamow's books, including Faust; Eine Historie, and she was a prolific letter writer. Copies of her letters are not well represented in the papers, but references in letters received indicate the scope of her writing.
During the early 1930s Barbara Gamow moved in circles that included the poet E. E. Cummings and his wife Marion Morehouse, scholars Edward Niles Hooker and Albert Guerard, filmmakers Stan Brakhage and John Larson, psychologists Evelyn Caldwell Hooker and Bernard Friedlander, and writers Raymong Peckham Holden, James Broughton, Charles Norman, Eda Lord, Sybille Bedford, Frances and Garner James, and Morgan Shepard. Letters from these and others provide source material for biographical studies of the correspondents and their acquaintances. Detailed letters over many years cover periods of youth, careers, and retirement. For the later years, there is material relating to old age, some aspects of the psychology of women, and discussions on parapsychology.
The Addition consists of George Gamow's correspondence with Martynas Yčas about the biological code and with Robert Herman about cosmology, arithmetic, and the big bang theory. Also included are letters by Gamow related to the works of Immanuel Velikovsky and other letters from Peter Brosche.
Organization of the Papers
The collection is arranged in seven series:
Family Correspondence, 1915-1973
General Correspondence, 1926-1975
Personal Correspondence of Barbara Gamow, 1928-1973
Speeches and Writings File, 1926-1970
Miscellany, 1931-1974
Addition, 1950-1967
Oversize, 1951-1970
Container List
- Family Correspondence, 1915-1973 (Box 1)
  Correspondence with members of the Gamow and Perkins families.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of family member.
  - Gamow family, Igor Rustem and Elfriede Reger Gamow, 1961-1973 (Box 1)
  - Perkins family
    - Barbara Perkins (Mrs. George Gamow), 1955-1958
    - Samuel Henry Perkins, 1915, 1938-1942
    - General, 1941-1951
- General Correspondence, 1926-1975 (Box 1-8)
  Letters received and some copies of letters sent, telegrams, postcards, and other enclosures.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - Ab Nordiska Uppslagsböcker, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Abalakin, Victor K., 1967-1971
  - Abelson, Philip H., 1967
  - All India Radio
  - Alpher, Ralph A., 1949-1975, (7 folders)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1964-1966
  - American Heritage Publishing Co., 1965-1969
  - Arons, Arnold, 1965-1966
  - Asimov, Isaac, 1967
  - "A" miscellaneous, 1939, 1957-1972
  - Baade, Hanni, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Badash, Lawrence, 1967
  - Balandin, Igor, 1964-1970
  - Barnes, Ruth, 1967
  - Berglin, Carl-Gustaf, 1963
  - Best, Marshall A., 1964
  - Bethovey, Larry, 1966
  - Beyan, Edward, 1966
  - Bhebha, H.
  - Birge, Raymond T., 1949
  - Blade, Richard, 1967
  - Blaedel, Niels, 1966
  - Bludman, Sidney, 1967
  - Bobrovnikoff, Nicholas T., 1969-1970
  - Börnstein, Ludwig, 1967
  - Bohr, Aage, 1963-1964
  - Bohr, Margrethe (Mrs. Niels), 1960-1969
  - Bohr, Marietta, 1967
  - Bohr, Niels, 1960-1961
  - Bok, Priscilla
  - Bose, Devendra M., 1959-1962
  - Boylen, Margaret and Al, circa 1956
  - Briggs, Richard I., 1960
  - Brissey, Catherine, 1968
  - Brittin, Janine, circa 1969
  - Brittin, Wesley E., 1962
  - Brogan, Hugh, 1965
  - Brosche, Peter, 1967
  - Brown, Harrison, 1956
  - Brown, Melvin L., Jr. 1967
  - Bueno, Antonio T., 1965
  - Bullard, Edward C., 1966-1967
  - Burbridge, Geoffrey, 1967
  - Burbridge, Margaret, 1967
  - Burlingham, Edward C., 1966
  - Burnell, Sylvia, 1959, 1968
  - "B" miscellaneous, 1930-1969
  - Cambridge University Press, 1964-1968
  - Campbell, Philip M., 1965-1967
  - Carmi, Gideon, 1967
  - Casimir, H. B. G., 1964
  - Chandrasekhar, S., 1967
  - Clark, Ronald W., 1968-1969
  - Cockcroft, Elizabeth, 1967
  - Cockcroft, John, 1966
  - Cohen, Erwin (Academic Press), 1966
  - Cohen, I. Bernard, 1967
  - Colie, Rosalie L., 1958
  - Constantindes [?], Panos, 1966-1967
  - Covici, Dorothy, 1967
  - Covici, Pascal (Viking Press), 1961-1964
  - Coyne, Donald, 1968
  - Crane, H. R. 1967
  - Cranshaw, T. E., 1964
  - Crick, Francis H. C., 1968
  - Critchfield, Charles L., 1944-1969
  - Cushman, Norman F., 1959-1960
  - "C" miscellaneous, 1951-1972
  - Davies, Gloria Evans, 1966 (Box 3)
  - Day, Frederick E., 1964
  - De Berry, Geneva, 1971-1972
  - De Guise, Dorothy A., 1967
  - Delbrück, Max, 1963-1969
  - Dennison, David M., 1967
  - Dicke, Robert, 1967
  - Dirac, Paul, 1967-1968
  - Dobzhansky, Natasha, 1961
  - Dodd, James, 1967-1971
  - Dollevoet, George, 1967
  - Dorozynski, Alexander, 1964-1965
  - Downing, Nancy, 1959
  - Duncan, Robert L., 1967
  - Dyson, Freeman, 1967
  - Eccleshare, Colin J., 1857-1965
  - Educational Services, 1965
  - Efimenco, Theodore, 1959
  - Ehricke, Krafft A., 1956
  - Einstein, Albert, 1948
  - Eleanor Roosevelt Institute for Cancer Research, 1967
  - Ellis, R. Hobart, Jr., 1967-1972
  - Encyclopaedia Britannica, 1968
  - "E" miscellaneous, 1960-1969
  - Fadiman, Clifton, 1964
  - Fahrney, D. S., 1967-1968
  - Fano, Ugo, 1968-1969
  - Feldman, Paul A., 1967-1968
  - Fermi, Laura, 1964-1967
  - Firestone, Miriam, 1965
  - Flanagan, Dennis, 1960, 1966
  - Fleming, Jessie, 1926-1927
  - Foster, Mary, 1969-1971
  - Fowler, William A., 1956, 1969
  - Friedman, William F. and Elizabeth S., 1957-1958, 1969
  - Friedr. Vieweg & Sohn, 1964
  - Frye, Betty (Mrs. William E.), 1966
  - Fujiwara, Masataka, 1959
  - "F" miscellaneous, 1959-1971, undated
  - Gavaudan, P., 1967
  - Geiss, Johan, 1968
  - Gieck, Jack E., 1968, 1972
  - Glass, I. I.., 1961
  - Gold, Tom, 1961
  - Goldberg, Edward D., 1962
  - Goldsmith, Margie Noyes, circa 1956-1963
  - Goodyear, C. C., 1960
  - Grabowski, Reinhard, 1964
  - Grandy, Walter T., Jr. 1968
  - Greenblatt, M. H., 1966
  - Greene, Jay E., 1965
  - Grinnell, Marjorie, 1958, 1971
  - Gruen, John and Jane Wilson, circa 1956-1960
  - Guéron, Jules and G., 1955-1969
  - "G" miscellaneous, 1955-1974
  - Hahn, Otto, 1965 (Box 4)
  - Haldane, J. B. S., 1959
  - Harris, Gertrude, 1952-1960
  - Heisenberg, Werner, 1965-1967
  - Hennessey, J. H., 1966
  - Herman, Robert, 1962-1970
  - Heuer, Kenneth, 1966
  - Houtermans, 1966
  - Humason, Milton, 1967
  - Hustwitt, Arthur, circa 1960
  - Hutchinson, Charles A., circa 1965
  - Hynek, J. Allen, 1964-1967
  - "H" miscellaneous, 1962-1970
  - Jensen, Hans
  - John Wiley & Sons, 1967
  - Jordan, Pascual, 1968
  - "J" miscellaneous, 1964-1971, undated
  - Katcher, David A., 1949
  - Keller, Geoffrey, 1961
  - Kempner, Aubrey, 1969-1971
  - Killen, John T., 1965
  - Kingsbury, Bruce F., 1959-1967, (2 folders)
  - Kingsford, Anthony, 1950-1971
  - Kistiakowsky, G. B., 1967
  - Klein, Oscar, 1967
  - Kolitschew, Konstantin D., 1958
  - Kudar, John C., 1961
  - Küpfer, R., 1968
  - Kuiper, Gerard P., 1956
  - "K" miscellaneous, 1959-1971
  - Laffineur, Marius, 1964
  - Lange vin, P., 1939
  - Lehmann, Christian, 1967
  - Leppelmeier, G. W., 1967
  - Libby, William F., 1956, 1968
  - Linda Hall Library, Kansas City, Mo., 1964
  - Lindberg, Gene, 1964-1968
  - Lipmann, Fritz, 1966, 1971
  - Lipsitz, Max H., 1966
  - Locke, John, 1960
  - Longair, Malcolm S., 1967-1968
  - Lovell, Bernard, 1967
  - Lynds, C. R., 1968
  - "L" miscellaneous, 1947-1975
  - McCue, Lillian de la Torre (Mrs. George), 1962-1971 (Box 5)
  - Macintyre, Elisabeth H. and Walter M., 1962-1972
  - Macorini, Edgardo, 1964-1966
  - McQuillen, Kenneth, 1968
  - Maki, Shinnosuke, 1959
  - Mansbridge, Ronald, 1953-1971
  - Marshall, Dorothy (Mrs. Robert W.), 1969-1972
  - Marx, Guido, 1949
  - Metropolis, Nicholas, 1967-1968
  - Miller, Dr., 1966t1
  - Mitchell, Lawrence, 1967
  - Moczorodynski, Margaret and Marie, 1964-1971
  - Moller, C., 1968t1
  - Moore, Ruth, 1966
  - Mordell, Mabel E., 1966, undated
  - Morris, Margaret R., 1969-1972
  - Mott, Ellis, 1963
  - Mott, Nevill, 1967, undated
  - Murphy, M. (Mrs. Edward Daniel), 1945-1964
  - "M" miscellaneous
  - Nachtrieb, Norman H., 1964
  - Nagata, George and Barbara, 1968, undated
  - Nakamura, Hiroshi, 1959-1968, undated
  - Nassau, J. J., 1961-1962
  - National Academy of Sciences, 1967-1968
  - Nature, 1967
  - Nelson, Jan.. 1969-1971
  - Nelson, Marian L., 1965, 1970-1972
  - Newton, Edna (Mrs. William C.), 1973
  - Nimitz, Chester W., 1950-1951
  - "N" miscellaneous, 1960-1973
  - Ollsen, Matthew and Elizabeth, 1969-1972
  - "O" miscellaneous, 1957-1968
  - Page, Thornton, 1967
  - Parthasarathi, Shrimathi G., 1959-1965
  - Peebles, P. J. E., 1967
  - Penzias, 1967
  - Pergamon Press, 1968
  - Physical Review, 1967
  - Porter, John, 1968
  - Prnetice-Hall, 1965-1967
  - Price, 1967
  - Prince, David, 1932
  - "P" miscellaneous, 1941-1971, undated
  - Rae, Stephen, 1964
  - Rainer, W. Gerald, 1967
  - Random House, 1964
  - Rashevsky, 1967
  - Reines, Frederick, 1969-1972
  - Revista de Occidente, 1963
  - Romania libera, 1967
  - Rosenberg, Fritz, 1969-1972
  - Rosenfeld, Beatrice, 1963-1968
  - Rosset, Barney, 1953-1958
  - Ryle, Martin, 1968
  - "R" miscellaneous, 1952-1972
  - Sahasrabudhe, M. B., 1967 (Box 6)
  - Sandage, Allan, 1965
  - Sciama, D. W., 1967
  - Science, 1967
  - Shapiro, Maurice M., 1962
  - Shepanski, John R., 1967
  - Sondermann, Fred A., 1964-1965
  - Soviet Peace Committee, 1966
  - Stokes, N. R. 1966
  - Szent-Györgyi, Albert, 1966, undated
  - Szent-Gyöogyi, Márta, 1962, undated
  - Szilard, Gertrud Weiss, 1964, 1971
  - "S" miscellaneous, 1951-1969
  - Tele-Lecture Series, 1965
  - Teller, Edward, 1956, 1960, 1967
  - Terrell, James, 1960-1961
  - Terry, Luther, 1964
  - Thomas, William A., 1968
  - Trousdale, Leon Herbert, 1970
  - Tuve, Merle, 1967
  - "T" miscellaneous, 1955-1971, undated
  - Uhlenbeck, George E., 1964
  - Ulam, Stanislaw M. and Francoise, 1961-1970
  - Umschau in Wissenschaft und Technik, 1967
  - United Nations Scientific and Cultural Organization, 1956
  - University of Colorado, Boulder, Colo., 1956-1973
  - Viking Press, 1963, 1968-1971
  - Von Lillienfeld-Watts, 1960-1972
  - Wagoner, Robert, 1967
  - Walton, Sadie and Harold F., 1959-1973
  - Weiner, Charles, 1970-1972
  - Wheeler, John A., 1956
  - Whitehead, A. Bruce, 1964
  - Wickenden, Elmira B., 1947-1971
  - Wigner, Eugene P., 1967
  - Wilkinson, D. H., 1967
  - Wittenberg, Elizabeth, 1970-1971
  - Wondhuysen, Henry L., 1964
  - Wright, Louis B., 1949-1960
  - "W" miscellaneous, 1930-1975
  - Yčas, Martynas, 1954-1972, (6 folders) (Box 7)
  - Yourgrau, Wolfgand and Thella, 1966-1971
  - Zion, Gene, circa 1953
  - Zirin, Harold, 1967
  - Unidentified, 1956-1967, undated
  - Letters concerning G. Gamow's "Basic Theories of Modern Physics," unpublished book manuscript, 1967-1973
  - Letters of congratulations upon marriage, 1958-1959
  - Letters of condolence upon the death of George Gamow, 1968 (Box 8)
  - Posthumous letters to George Gamow, 1968-1974, (7 folders)
  - Posthumous letters concerning translation rights, 1968-1970
- Personal Correspondence of Barbara Gamow, 1928-1973 (Box 9-14)
  Letters received and some copies of letters sent, with attachments, literary material, drawings, and related material.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent and therein chronologically.
  - Bedford, Sybille See Container 13, Lord, Eda (Box 9)
  - Bowen, Mary, 1958-1965, (3 folders)
  - Bowman, Brigitte (Mrs. Howard), 1966-1968
  - Brakhage, Stan and Jane, 1960-1972
  - Broughton, James, 1938-1972, (3 folders)
  - Bueno, J. R. de la Torre, Jr., 1937-1948
  - Chomeley, Elsie, 1939-1944
  - Christman, Henry and Zoë Fales, 1944-1970
  - Collins, Peter, and Elizabeth D. Logan, 1958-1971
  - Cummings, E. E., and Marion Morehouse, 1954-1969
  - Cushen, Karen Lind (Mrs. John Richard), 1955-1973
  - DeMourges, Odette, 1965-1973 (Box 10)
  - DePierri, Kate Pinsdorf (Mrs. Gail Borden), 1964-1973, (3 folders)
  - Dirac, Manci (Mrs. Paul), 1966-1973
  - Donnell, Radka (Mrs. Frank), 1963-1973
  - Friedlander, Bernard Z., 1954-1973
  - Gamow, George (Box 11)
    - 1957-1968, (2 folders)
    - Health charts, 1947-1968
  - Guérard, Albert Léon, 1929-1956
  - Hein, Piet, 1961-1962
  - Hoerlin, Kate and Herman, circa 1963-1972
  - Holden, Raymond Peckham
    - 1932-1939, (10 folders)
    - 1940-1973, (7 folders) (Box 12)
  - Holdsworth, Betsy, 1969-1972
  - Hooker, Edward Niles, 1949-1950
  - Hooker, Edward Niles and Evelyn Caldwell, 1951-1957
  - James, Frances Theiss and Garner, 1945-1958
  - Kirby, Marshall, 1928-1934
  - Komatsu, Mieko, 1959-1972 (Box 13)
  - Larson, John and Marion Agnes, 1960-1972
  - Lennartz, Beatrice, 1968-1972
  - Loewy, Hanna M., 1963-1973
  - Lord, Eda, 1961-1972
  - Marquette, Mary, 1960-1972
  - Martin, John, 1931-1939
  - Maxwell, Helene Johanne (Mrs. Edward Hooker, Mrs. Joseph Brewer), 1940-1970
  - Maxwell, William Quentin, 1954-1969
  - McCandless, Ruth (Mrs. R. S.) and Duncan, 1960-1973
  - Newell, Hope, 1959-1965 (Box 14)
  - Nisbet, Ada, 1949-1970
  - Norman, Charles, 1941-1973, (4 folders)
  - Pardo, Mimi Hayes (Mrs. Paul), 1958-1973
  - Peters, Agnes D., 1961-1971
  - Pierotti, Dorothy (Mrs. Ray), 1969-1973
  - Rathbone, Augusta, 1968-1973
  - Ratner, Peggy (Mrs. Marc), 1961-1973
  - Schuyler, William J., 1962-1969
  - Shepard, Morgan See Container 13, Martin, John
  - Shreve, Agnes A., 1970-1973
  - Smythe, Daniel Webster, 1937-1948
  - Sutherland, Gilberte (Mrs. Donald), 1964-1973
  - Tucker, Elizabeth (Mrs. Shepard S.), 1971-1973
  - Wedmore, Keith, 1957-1962
- Speeches and Writings File, 1926-1970 (Box 15-27)
  Books and articles in manuscript, typescript, galley, and printed form, including some correspondence, reviews, and related material, and speeches and book reviews.
  Arranged by type of material. Articles are arranged chronologically and books are arranged alphabetically by title, with printed copies at the end.
  - Articles (Box 15)
    - 1926-1949, (62 folders)
    - 1950-1969, (40 folders) (Box 16)
    - Undated, (10 folders) (Box 17)
  - Book reviews
    - Niels Bohr, by Ruth Moore
    - Otto Hann, translated and edited by Willy Ley
  - Speeches
    - Remarks at Cosmological Conference, undated
    - Caracas, Venezuela, Conference, 1957
  - Books
    - "Basic Theories of Modern Physics," manuscripts and illustrations, 1967, (9 folders); (12 folders) (Box 18)
    - Biography of Physics (1961) (Box 19)
    - Biography of the Earth (1941), manuscript inserts, French edition, circa 1955 (Box 20)
    - "Collisions of Galaxies and Cosmology," chapter typescript and Spanish translation, 1962
    - Gravity (1962), illustrations
    - Matter, Earth, and Sky (1958)
      - Manuscripts and typescripts, (15 folders); (21 folders); (22 folders); (20 folders) (Box 21, Box 22, Box 23)
    - Mr. Tompkins in Paperback (1965) (Box 24)